Guide to the Records of the Army and Navy Club of New York 1933-1973 MS 3080
New-York Historical Society
Army and Navy Club of New York records
1933-1973
New-York Historical Society
MS 3080
5.65 Linear feet in 6 record cartons
The Military-Naval Club, renamed in 1960 the Army and Navy Club of New York, was a social organization for veterans that existed in New York City for much of the mid 20th century. This collection includes their administrative records, primarily their records of former members along with meeting minutes.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
Series I: Meeting Minutes
Series II: Membership Records
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Scope and Contents
These materials were created by the Military-Naval Club, which in 1960 renamed itself the Army and Navy Club of New York. All of the records date from 1933 to 1973. There are meeting minutes for that entire 40 year span, along with membership files for their non-active members as of 1973. There is one folder of income tax information for one employee of the club.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were likely donated to New-York Historical Society by the Army and Navy Club of New York between 1973 and 1985.
Historical Note
The Army and Navy Club of New York was founded in 1933 under the name of the Military-Naval Club. According to their Articles of Incorporation, their purpose was to "promote social interaction of the commissioned officers, both active and retired, of the military and naval forces of the United States of America and foreign country and such other persons as may be qualified for membership hereunder, to establish a common meeting ground for such officers and other persons within the City of New York." They originally used space belonging to the Columbia Club, and for many years were located at 4 East 43rd St.
United States -- Armed Forces -- Military life.; Veterans -- New York (State); Armed Forces.; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1939-1945; Korean War, 1950-1953.; Patriotic societies -- United States; United States. Army; United States. Navy
- Series I: Meeting Minutes, 1933-1973; 2 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  The Minutes of the Board of Directors Meetings consist of summaries of their monthly meetings. Issues would be discussed such as the financial situation of the club, new member applications, and members who were being removed for lack of payment of dues. There are monthly lists of the officers of the organization and balance sheets of their assets and liabilities.
  The minutes of the Annual Meetings contain similar information, summarized for the entire membership. They discussed finances, election of new officers, and news about upcoming and past events.
  There is also one folder of tax filings for a deceased employee.
  Arrangement
  Minutes are arranged reverse chronologically, which is the order in which they were received, however the archivist put the minutes into acid-free folders. The tax forms are in the final folder of the series, and are also arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - Board Meeting Minutes (8 folders), 1946-1968 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-8)
  - Board Meeting Minutes (4 folders), 1933-1945 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Annual and Special Meeting Minutes (3 folders), 1934-1973 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - W3 Tax Filing, 1962-1966 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
- Series II: Membership Records, 1933-1973; 3.65 Linear feet
  Membership files include applications of former, deceased, and rejected members. There are no membership files for those members who were active in the Club at the time the collection was donated, which was likely in the mid 1970s. Nearly all members who are listed as dropped were marked as such for the failure to pay their yearly dues.
  Membership applications became more detailed throughout time, but include information such as the name, date, and place of birth of the applicant, the names of the applicant's parents, the applicant's religion, occupation, educational history, military service, and character references. There is usually correspondence to and from the applicant attached to the application.
  Records were left more or less in the order in which they were received. Membership files are arranged by category of member, and alphabetically within each category.
  - Resigned Members, A-K (9 folders), 1935-1969 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-9)
  - Resigned Members, K-W (8 folders), 1933-1971 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1-8)
  - Resigned Members, W-Z, 1938-1971 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
  - Rejected Members, A-Z, 1936-1973 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
  - Dropped Members, A-W (10 folders), 1933-1972 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2-11)
  - Dropped Members, W, 1937-1972 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
  - Members who Failed to Pay Initiation Fee (2 folders), 1934-1964 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2-3)
  - Deceased Members, A-Z (4 folders), 1933-1970 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4-7)
  - Honorary Members, A-Z, 1936-1967 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8)